<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary sitting at Christs feet A sermon preached at the funerall of Mris Mary Swaine, the wife of Mr William Swaine, at Saint Buttolphs without Aldersgate. Declaring her christian life, and comfortable death, for the encouraging of all christian gentlewomen, and others, to walke in the steps of this religious gentlewoman already departed. By Lancelot Langhorne, preacher of the word of God.</title>
            <author>Langhorne, Lancelot.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105859</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841585</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6179</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6179)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 720:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mary sitting at Christs feet A sermon preached at the funerall of Mris Mary Swaine, the wife of Mr William Swaine, at Saint Buttolphs without Aldersgate. Declaring her christian life, and comfortable death, for the encouraging of all christian gentlewomen, and others, to walke in the steps of this religious gentlewoman already departed. By Lancelot Langhorne, preacher of the word of God.</title>
                  <author>Langhorne, Lancelot.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by N. Okes] for Arthur Iohnson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through, and some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6179:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6179:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MARY SITTING AT CHRISTS FEET.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Mary Swaine,</hi> the wife of Mr <hi>William Swaine, at</hi> Saint <hi>Buttolphs</hi> without <hi>Alderſgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Declaring her Chriſtian life, and comfortable death, for the encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of all Chriſtian Gentlewomen, and others, to walke in the ſteps of this religious gentlewoman already departed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Lancelot Langhorne,</hi> Preacher of the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ade ſed incultus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 31.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Who ſhall finde a vertuous woman? For her price is farre aboue the pearles.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Arthur Iohnſon,</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6179:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6179:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull and vertuous Lady, <hi>Chriſtiana Leueſon,</hi> wife to the Right Worſhipfull, Sir <hi>Iohn Leueſon,</hi> Knight, grace and peace in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering with my ſelfe, that our nature is ſuch, as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure that theſe praiſes ſhould be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto others (though they duly deſerue them) which we thinke our ſelues worthy
<pb facs="tcp:6179:3"/> of (though indeed moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy) I reſolued with my ſelfe to commit this Sermon to the patronage of ſome one, who might bee able to defend the truth of it againſt the malicious traducing, and repining of the enuious, and amongſt many, I could find none more fit then your ſelfe; partly becauſe with MARY, you haue choſen the better part, and that (according to your name) your heart is the ſeat and temple of vertue: partly by reaſon of that long continued loue &amp; familiarity which hath beene betweene you; as alſo becauſe of that full experience, and true triall
<pb facs="tcp:6179:3"/> you had of her ſpotleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation: therefore pardon my boldneſſe, and as you loue vertue, and haue the praiſes of this rare Iewell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed in your breaſt: ſo let them haue your louing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and holy imitation, to your vnſpeakeable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in this life, and the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſaluation of your owne ſoule in the life to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the Lord,</hi> Lancelot Langhorne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6179:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6179:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONDEMNE</hi> not me, gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for publishing this Sermon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſeeke not my ſelfe, but the continual remembrance of this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Gentlewoman vpon earth; and was moued thereunto by perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others, who alſo procured it to bee licenced. Accuſe me not of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery: for my conſcience beares me witneſſe (as thouſands can alſo teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie) that all I haue ſaid is but a part of her praiſes. Tax not my too much breuity, that I haue not enlarged it
<pb facs="tcp:6179:5"/> as I might, becauſe I would haue no more printed then was firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; and this length beſt befits a Funerall, which (like life of man) is but a ſpanne long.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, L. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6179:5"/>
            <head>MARY SITTING AT CHRISTS FEET.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE. 10.42.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> hath choſen the better part, which ſhall not be taken away from her.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Story, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by the <hi>Euangeliſt,</hi> there is mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of two Siſters, two Actions, &amp; a two-fold Cenſure vpon both, by our Sauiour; The Siſters, <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary:</hi> the Actions,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6179:6"/> 
               <hi>Martha troubled her ſelfe about many things;</hi> Mary <hi>ſate at Ieſus feete, and heard his preaching:</hi> whereupon <hi>Martha</hi> was diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that <hi>Mary</hi> did not helpe her: But Chriſt anſwers, <hi>that</hi> Martha <hi>was troubled about many things, whereas one was needfull, and that</hi> Mary <hi>had choſen the better part, which ſhould not bee taken away from her.</hi> Chriſt loued them both, and they both ſhew their loue to Chriſt: <hi>Martha</hi> in enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining him, <hi>Mary</hi> in hearing him: For as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith: <hi>Laude digna Marthae hoſpitalitas: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> is praiſe-worthy for her hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality; but in that ſhe buſied herſelfe aboue meaſure, and did not with <hi>Mary, chooſe the better part,</hi> therefore Chriſt blames her. <hi>Non Dominus opus reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, ſed munus diſtinxit,</hi> ſaith S. <note n="a" place="margin">Aug. Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>27.</hi> de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> The Lord doth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6179:6"/> not blame her worke, but doth diſtinguiſh of both their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Nec</hi> Martha <hi>in bono miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio reprehenditur, ſed</hi> Maria <hi>quòd meliorem partem ſibi elegerit ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur,</hi> ſaith S.<note n="b" place="margin">Ambroſ. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Luc.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon this place: Neither is <hi>Martha</hi> blamed in her good ſeruice, but <hi>Mary</hi> is preferred, becauſe <hi>ſhee choſe the better part.</hi> Martha <hi>in domum ſuam recepit Saluatorem in terris:</hi> Maria <hi>potiùs cogitat quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodùm ſuſcipiatur ab eo in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, non manufacta, ſed aeterna in coelis</hi> ſaith S.<note n="c" place="margin">Bernard de aſſump. Mariae Ser. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard: Martha</hi> receiues her Sauiour into her houſe vpon earth: <hi>Mary</hi> rather thinkes how ſhe may bee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by him in a houſe<note n="d" place="margin">2 Co. 5.1</note> 
               <hi>Not made with hands, but eternall in the Heauens.</hi> The one is buſie in entertaining Chriſt into her houſe, the other is carefull to receiue him into her heart. And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6179:7"/> this Chriſt preferres before the other: <hi>That</hi> Mary <hi>had choſen the better part, which ſhall not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some, by <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> vnderſtand the <hi>Actiue</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue</hi> life; that they muſt be as ſiſters, both dwelling in one houſe, both lodging in one heart: or that they are the two <hi>Wings of the Soule,</hi> by which it ſoares vp from earth to <hi>Heauen.</hi> And why may we not apply them to the <hi>Body</hi> and the <hi>Soule</hi> of euery faithfull Chriſtian? both beloued of Chriſt, both entertaining him: two ſiſters v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in life, and ſeparated only by death: The <hi>Body</hi> (the elder ſiſter) is troubled about many things, as <hi>delicate feeding, warme Clothing, dayly Suſtentation,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>Continuall recreation:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Soule (Mary)</hi> thinkes one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6179:7"/> thing neceſſary: <hi>To ſit at Chriſts feet, and to heare his preaching. Martha</hi> (the <hi>Body</hi>) is here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to our eies: <hi>Mary</hi> (her bleſſed <hi>Soule</hi>) reſts at the feet of Ieſus Chriſt, which ſits at the right hand of God in heauen.</p>
            <p>But leauing <hi>Allegories,</hi> let vs fall vpon the literal ſence, which is Chriſts approbation of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> choice, and leauing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Martha</hi> with <hi>Mary,</hi> let vs compare <hi>Mary</hi> with <hi>Mary;</hi> this <hi>Mary</hi> before our eies, with <hi>Mary</hi> in the text: one commended by God, the other no leſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable before <hi>God;</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> vouch ſafeth with his owne mouth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the one: ſo the tongue of an Angell were but ſufficient to praiſe the other: For as the Philoſophers ſay: <hi>Excellens ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectum corr umpit ſenſum:</hi> The brightneſſe of the obiect doth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6179:8"/> weaken the ſenſe: So my mouth is too rude to ſpeake the praiſes of ſo excellent a creature: when I haue ſaid all I can, I ſhall ſay too little. <hi>Momus</hi> may well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me of ſpeaking too rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or too ſparingly, but not of flattery.</p>
            <p>I feare nothing but ſinking, while I wade into the depth of her vertues: Therefore, with <note n="f" place="margin">Math. 14.30.31.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> vpon the water, I will take Chriſt by the hand, and from Chriſts mouth ſpeake <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> commendation: I come not to extoll fleſh and bloud, but to deſcribe thoſe graces God had endowed her withall, and not onely from report (for I haue conuerſed with her almoſt theſe foure yeares, and was preſent with her the moſt part of her ſickneſſe) and ſure I am, out of mine owne experience, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6179:8"/> 
               <hi>Mary</hi> with <hi>Mary hath choſen the better part, which ſhall not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words obſerue in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The perſon approued.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Her wiſedome for which Chriſt approues her.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The perſon commended, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> her wiſedome for which ſhe is commended: <hi>That ſhee did chooſe the better part, which ſhall not be taken from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In her <hi>wiſedome</hi> two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The Action.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Obiect.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The action, <hi>That ſhee did chooſe;</hi> the obiect, <hi>the better part, which ſhould not be taken from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Obiect</hi> two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The Excellency.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Perpetuity.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The excellency, that it was <hi>Better:</hi> The perpetuity, <hi>It ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6179:9"/> neuer be taken from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In each of theſe, three things ſhall be handled.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Maries Commendation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Maries Imitation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Our Application.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Maries Commendation:</hi> laid downe in the Text: <hi>That ſhee did chooſe the better part, which ſhall not be taken, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maries Imitation:</hi> the ſame with the Text: <hi>That ſhee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hath choſen the better part, which ſhall not, &amp;c,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Application:</hi> taught from the Text, <hi>That wee alſo make choice of the better part, which ſhall not &amp;c.</hi> That ſo wee may make theſe two <hi>Maries</hi> our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, to follow in the way to <hi>Heauen,</hi> that thereby wee may find fauour with God and men, That with <hi>Mary</hi> we may liue in Gods feare, and with <hi>Mary</hi> die
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6179:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> in Gods fauour: of theſe in their order, and firſt of the perſon approued.</p>
            <p>The perſon approued is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Chriſt <hi>Mary:</hi> we finde but three <hi>Maries</hi> ſpoken of in the Goſpell, and all for good: <hi>Mary,</hi> the mother of Ieſus, <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> which (as moſt affirme) is this <hi>Mary</hi> in my Text: and <hi>Mary,</hi> the mother of <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Ioſes.</hi> One beares Chriſt in her wombe, the other waſhes his feete with her teares, and wipes them with the haire of her head,<note place="margin">Her Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</note> and here <hi>ſits at Chriſts feete:</hi> the third, with the two other, ſtand by his croſſe, when he is crucified, and ſeeke him in his graue after hee was buried. Wee finde not ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vertuous woemen of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name in Scripture, not that the name makes them the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6179:10"/> holier, but that their vertues make the remembrance of their names bleſſed, I could ſtand vpon the letters of the name if it were ſo profitable,<note place="margin">Maria.</note> (M) ſtanding vpon three baſes or feete,<note place="margin">M</note> to ſignifie their ſtedfaſt faith in the bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> one God and three perſons:<note place="margin">A</note> 
               <hi>(a)</hi> an interiection of ſorrowing, <hi>their repentance:</hi>
               <note place="margin">R</note> 
               <hi>(r)</hi> with two bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches like a tree, <hi>the ſweete fruite of their vertue and holineſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">I</note> 
               <hi>(i)</hi> the leaſt of the letters, <hi>Their great humility:</hi>
               <note place="margin">A</note> 
               <hi>(a)</hi> the firſt letter in the Alphabet, and the laſt in the name, <hi>Their charity;</hi> the cheifeſt of all vertues, becauſe it <note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 13 13. 2 <hi>Maries</hi> imitation. Luk. 11.27.28.</note> 
               <hi>continues laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Mary</hi> paralels the other <hi>Maries;</hi> She bore Chriſt, though not in her wombe, yet (which is more) in her heart: often ſhee waſhed his feete with the teares
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6179:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> of repentance: ſtood at his Croſſe, to the waſhing away of her ſinnes in his bloud: often ſhe ſought him in his graue, to the mortifying of her ſinnes: and daily ſought him at the right hand of God in <hi>Heauen,</hi> for the pardon of her ſinnes; we ſhall finde more vertues in her life, then letters in her name. <hi>Mary</hi> by interpretation is as much as <hi>Stella maris,</hi> the Starre of the Sea, which ſtanding immouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the midſt of heauen, doth direct the Mariners. As the Starres are fixed in the volume of the heauens, ſo <hi>Mary</hi> in my Text, is a fixed Starre in the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of Gods written booke: A direction for all Chriſtians to the <hi>Hauen of happineſſe.</hi> Though this <hi>Mary</hi> preſented to our eies, be not in Gods written booke, yet in the <hi>Lambs booke of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6179:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> life, her name is written in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> A Star, for <hi>purity</hi> of heart: A Starre, for the <hi>ſhining</hi> light of life and conuerſation, A fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Starre, for her heart was fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the Lord, yet neuer moued backward, nor neuer ſtood ſtill, but as <hi>(The Sunne in the firmament) reioyced to runne her courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Our Ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication.</note>For our Application: Let vs become ſhining Starres, grace our names with vertues, that with <hi>Mary,</hi> the memoriall of our names may bee bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Wiſedome as (<hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) conſiſteth cheifly in <hi>Chooſing</hi> and <hi>Refuſing:</hi> In <hi>chooſing the Good,</hi> and <hi>Refuſing the Euill:</hi> The firſt thing in her wiſedome is, <hi>Elegit;</hi> The Action: <hi>Shee hath choſen;</hi> But how was it in <hi>Maries</hi> power to <hi>chooſe the better part?</hi> Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ciuill actions we haue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6179:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Free-will,</hi> to chooſe or refuſe, yet as the ſame actions are good, we haue no ability at all in our ſelues. <hi>Of our ſelues wee are not able to thinke one good thought:</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle:,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation</note> Power we haue to thinke, but no power to thinke that which is good: To come to Church, to heare the word, is a <hi>Ciuill Action;</hi> we haue power to come, or not to come, but to come with a <hi>deſire and loue to the word, to glorifie God for the ſauing of our ſoules,</hi> by <hi>Nature</hi> we haue no power at all. Therefore in that <hi>Mary</hi> chooſeth, it is <hi>Actus Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi> an act of Nature; but in that <hi>ſhee chooſeth the better part,</hi> it is <hi>Actus Gratiae,</hi> an act of Grace: He that commends her for her choice, gaue her power <hi>to chooſe the beter part. Elegit,</hi> as one ſaith, <hi>(id eſt) Deus volentem trahit, &amp;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6179:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> coronat ſua dona in nobis, vt dica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur feciſſe &amp; elegiſſe nos, quae ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in nobis eſt operatus.</hi> She hath choſen (that is) God drew her being made willing, and he doth crowne his giftes in vs, that we may be ſaid to haue done, and to haue choſen thoſe things, which he himſelfe hath wrought in vs. Vnleſſe God did firſt chooſe vs, we ſhould neuer chooſe him: <hi>Yee haue not choſen mee, but I haue choſen you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.19</note>
               <hi>We loue him, becauſe he loued vs firſt,</hi> ſaith his Apoſtle. For euen as the heat of the Sunne falling vpon our body encreaſeth our heat: ſo the feeling of Gods loue towards vs, makes vs loue God againe; <hi>His election of vs, makes vs elect and chooſe him.</hi> The word in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hath choſen:</hi> that ſhe did
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6179:12"/> not embrace the pleaſures of this world <hi>all her life,</hi> and made choice of the <hi>better part,</hi> at <hi>her death;</hi> they that do deferre it ſo long, it is to be feared, it will be too late: for <hi>Sera poenitentia nòn eſt vera poenitentia:</hi> Late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is ſeldome true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; but <hi>Elegit, Shee hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So this <hi>Mary</hi> being a choſen and elect veſſell of God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Maries</hi> imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from the <hi>Wombe,</hi> by Gods grace did <hi>chooſe the better part:</hi> not at her <hi>Death,</hi> but <hi>all the time of her pilgrimage,</hi> ſhee led an <hi>Angelicall</hi> and <hi>holy life.</hi> This <hi>Good part</hi> was her <hi>Treaſure</hi> all her <hi>Life,</hi> and at her <hi>Death</hi> (as you ſhall heare) ſhee had the comfort of it.</p>
            <p>For our application;<note place="margin">3 Our appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> let vs not wallow in the pleaſure of ſinne all our life, and thinke it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6179:13"/> ſhall bee in our power at our <hi>Death, to chooſe the better part:</hi> but with this <hi>Mary</hi> let euery one of vs prepare &amp; prouide for the time to come, &amp; be ſure that we can ſay euery one to his owne ſoule, <hi>Elegi: I haue choſen the better part, which ſhal not be taken away from mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I come to the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,</hi> the <hi>Center</hi> and heart of the body of my Text: <hi>The better part: That as</hi> Martha <hi>was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about many things, ſhe had choſen the better part, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt here vſeth a <hi>metaphor</hi> taken from heires that diuide their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: for amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> and other <hi>Nations,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, there was a cuſtome, that the eldeſt child muſt diuide the inheritance into as equall parts as he could, and then the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt did firſt chooſe: So <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6179:13"/> and <hi>Mary</hi> (being ſiſters) they diuide Chriſt as an inheritance, betweene them: <hi>Martha</hi> diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as being the eldeſt,<note place="margin">1 Her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and <hi>Mary</hi> did chooſe, as beeing the yongeſt: <hi>And ſhe choſe the better part, &amp;c.</hi> Now the part that ſhe did chooſe, is, that <hi>ſhee ſate at Chriſts feet, and heard his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> ſought her ſaluation, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected all, in regard of this: eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it no profit to <hi>gaine the whole world, and to looſe her ſoule.</hi> It is ſaid by ſome, that <hi>ſhe neuer looked man in the face, after her conuerſion, but Chriſt:</hi> And this we may note, that <hi>ſhe neuer came vnto Chriſt, but ſhe fell downe at his feet: When ſhe annointed him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 7.38. Iohn. 11.32 Iohn. 12.3. Mat. 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>When ſhe beſought him for her brother</hi> Lazarus: <hi>At the ſupper in Bethania: After his Reſurrection: And now when ſhe heard him preach.</hi> And herein appeared her
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6179:14"/> 
               <hi>great humility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Maries</hi> imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note>But this <hi>Mary</hi> hath not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len at <hi>Chriſts feet</hi> fiue times, but all the daies of her life: how ſhe loued the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> the <hi>Houſe of Praier?</hi> She conſidered that one thing was needfull: though ſhe had but a weake bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet ſhee reſpected neither health, nor life, ſo ſhe might ſit at <hi>Chriſts feet,</hi> &amp; heare his word. How ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did ſhe fall at Chriſts feet to pray vnto him? Shee praied, not three times a day, with <hi>Daniel,</hi> but <hi>Continually.</hi> I haue often obſerued her, that all the time ſhe was not imployed in houſhold buſineſſe, ſhe ſpent it in meditation and praier; and if at any time ſhe vſed ordinary recreation, to beare her <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi> and his freinds company, her affections were ſo wholly ſet vpon heauenly things, as ſhe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6179:14"/> often vſed this gracious and ſanctified ſpeech: <hi>This is a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing away of the time, but no redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the time.</hi> And ſuch a care ſhe had to prepare her ſelfe for an other world, to haue oyle in her lampe, when the <hi>Bridegrome</hi> came, as ſhe was ſtill afraid, leſt <hi>God</hi> ſhould take her away when <hi>ſhe was ſo imployed:</hi> Her whole care and deſire was (with <hi>Mary</hi>) to ſit at <hi>Chriſts feet,</hi> to heare God ſpeaking vnto her, or elſe to ſpeake vnto God by praier: And the oftner ſhe fell downe and kiſt her <hi>Sauiours feet,</hi> the more deſirous ſhe was: The oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhe heard the word, the oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhe praied: the more ardent and ſtrong her deſires were, the more Gods graces were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in her. And as it is ſaid, that when <hi>Anthaeus</hi> wreſtled with <hi>Hercules,</hi> the oftner hee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6179:15"/> fell to the ground, receiuing ſtrength thereby, hee became more valiant in fight: So the oftner <hi>ſhe fell downe at the feet of her Sauiour,</hi> and wreſtled with God, the more ſtrength ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued againſt the aſſaults of ſin and Sathan, and roſe vp more rich in grace then before.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Our appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>For our application: Let vs learne to humble our ſelues at the feet of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and then we ſhall profit by his word <hi>to the ſauing of our ſoules:</hi> and our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall be heard, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith: <hi>Caſt downe your ſelues before God, and he will lift you vp,</hi> The higher men intend to build, the lower they lay the <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> So God will neuer exalt thee, except thou beeſt firſt humbled, and fall downe at his feet: Chriſt himſelfe was not exalted,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> but by <hi>Humiliation:</hi> the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6179:15"/> loweſt <hi>Vallies</hi> are moſt fruitfull: <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to the Humble:</hi> yet few imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <hi>Mary</hi> herein, they will ſet Chriſt at their feet, <hi>Treade the bloud of the Lambe vnder their feet:</hi> But they will not <hi>fall downe at the feet of Chriſt,</hi> and (with <hi>Mary) chooſe the better part, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs come to the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> of this <hi>Obiect,</hi> in that he calles it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>The good part. Auguſtine</hi> he turnes it <hi>meliorem partem:</hi> the better part: The word in the originall is the <hi>Poſitiue,</hi> but I vnderſtand the wordes to bee ſpoken <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiuely,</hi> that Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares <hi>Maries</hi> part with <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha's,</hi> and that the <hi>Poſitiue</hi> is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put for the <hi>Comparatiue,</hi> as ſome tranſlate it, <hi>meliorem,</hi> the better part, or elſe for the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatiue,</hi> as others tranſlate it,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6179:16"/> 
               <hi>Optimam,</hi> the beſt part, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.8. where the word is in the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>It is good for thee;</hi> and yet the <hi>Poſitiue</hi> is there put for the <hi>Comparatiue: It is better for thee, &amp;c.</hi> as we tranſlate it: So here it is called the good part, which is better then <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha's,</hi> and alſo the beſt: for they haue the <hi>beſt part that haue the Lord for their portion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Maries</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</note> This <hi>good part</hi> is that <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> the cheife good, euen Chriſt Ieſus and his merites, in compariſon of which,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> all things elſe are but <hi>Dongue:</hi> for hauing Chriſt ſhe had all things; no graces which did belong to the comfort, or ſauing of her ſoule, could bee wanting vnto her: for <hi>She did chooſe to heare the word, which is the power of God to ſaluation, to euery one that beleeueth,</hi> which wrought grace in her heart,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6179:16"/> which is crowned with glory in heauen.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Maries</hi> imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But let vs leaue <hi>Mary</hi> in our Text, and behold what rich gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this good part wrought in the breaſt of this our <hi>Mary;</hi> which appeared both in her life, and at her death. Firſt, for her piety towards God; <hi>She was truly religious,</hi> her <hi>Profeſſion</hi> was not <hi>Hypocriticall,</hi> nor <hi>Verball,</hi> but ſhe feared God with her heart: For her <hi>conuerſation in the world;</hi> it was <hi>Pure and vnſpotted:</hi> ſo as <hi>Enuy</hi> might carpe, but <hi>malice</hi> could not condemne: ſhe was of wonderfull <hi>meeke and quiet ſpirit,</hi> which afore God is a thing much ſet by, and as they that knew her had experience of it: ſo eſpecially her <hi>Husband,</hi> with whom ſhee liued for the ſpace of 33 yeares, and I haue heard him often ſay: That in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6179:17"/> all that time he neuer receiued an vnkinde word fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her mouth, or cauſe of diſcontent; where alſo wee may behold <hi>Her great wiſedome in Houſhold go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment:</hi> And moreouer, ſo great was her loue vnto her <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> as ſhe expreſſed it in her exceeding great loue, and care of his owne kindred: for ſhee loued him in them, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both in her life, and at her death. Her greateſt and laſt care vpon earth was, that ſeeing God <hi>had giuen him no children by her, he would be a father in prouiding for them, which were left vnto her, as to a mother.</hi> Againe, for her modeſty and grauity ſhee was matchleſſe: In her attire ſhe condemned the monſtrous pride of this age, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt woemen,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.3.</note> as the Apoſtle enioines vertuous wommen:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6179:17"/> Her apparell was not outward in broidred haire, or gold put about, or in putting on of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, but the <hi>Hid man</hi> of her heart was vncorrupt. Her cariage generally towards all was ſo milde, ſo wiſe, ſo diſcreet, ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, as it pleaſed all, wrought an admiration in the eies of all at her death, cauſed great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation in the hearts of all, drew teares from the eies of all;<note place="margin">Her name by her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Winhall.</hi>
               </note> and laſtly did <hi>Win-all</hi> that knew her. And as all ſhall miſſe her, ſo eſpecially the poore: for ſhee was ſo charitable, as if ſhe were made of the bowels of mercy &amp; compaſſion: full of pittie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the diſtreſſed, full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards the needy: her poore neighbours ſhal haue cauſe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bewaile her death: <hi>For ſhe ſtretched out her hand to the poore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 31.20</note> 
               <hi>and put forth her hand to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6179:18"/> needy:</hi> And what ſhee had, ſhee beſtowed it not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vaine toies, but laid it vpon the backes of the poore members of Chriſt, in clothing the naked, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the hungry; <hi>She</hi> was a Nurſe to the Fatherleſſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, eies to the blinde, feet to the lame; the bleſſing of them that were ready to periſh, came vpon her. Thus in her life ſhee choſe the better part, laid vp her treaſure in heauen, a good foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the time to come, that when Chriſt ſhall giue the laſt Sentence, ſhee ſhall heare theſe comfortable words: <hi>Come thou bleſſed of my Father, inherite the kingdome prepared for thee: For what thou haſt done vnto one of theſe, thou haſt done vnto me.</hi> And when God ſummoned her with ſickneſſe to leaue this world, and with the <hi>New-yeare</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:6179:18"/> to ſet her heart in order for a new world, though her whole life were a meditation of death, her whole life a preparation for death; yet out of her great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, ſhee confeſt her great vnworthineſſe at the feet of her Sauiour, that ſhe was an <hi>Vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruant:</hi> and being taught by the Spirit of God, that none ſhall bee ſaued, but ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end, ſhe ſtill prayed vnto our Sauiour for perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: and (which is worthy to bee obſerued) though through the whole courſe of her life, her ſoule was ſtill powred out in praier vnto her God, yet ſhee found by experience, that when the body is weake with ſicknes, the heart is not ſo fit for praier. Let vs heare her words, which ſhe vttered vnto two reuerend Diuines,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Chark.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Paget.</hi>
               </note> and often repeated to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6179:19"/> vs that were preſent with her in time of her ſickneſſe: <hi>Let none deferr their preparation, nor their praiers vnto the bed of their ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for then the mind is too much troubled with the greife of the body, to be imployed as they ought in ſpirituall exerciſes:</hi> Yet ſhe was ſtrong in faith, and had ſtrong conſolations, and ſtil did caſt her hope (the ſure and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt anchor of her ſoule) vpon Chriſt Ieſus, the fore-runner in heauen: and often ſhee deſired in her praiers that Death might not be bitter vnto her, to ſhake her faith, or remoue her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from her God, but that ſhe might haue an eaſie paſſage; And behold the Lords mercy; all that day before ſhee depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (though her memory was good, &amp; her ſenſes perfect) yet ſhe ſaid ſhe felt no paine, and ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6179:19"/> could not bee perſwaded that Death was ſo neare. But ſhe left the world with no more ſtriuing or greife, then if ſhee had beene caſt into a ſlumber, or fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt: <hi>Quòd fuit à dolore mortis extraneus:</hi> That hee was freed from the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of Death: and as it is written of HENOCH <hi>That wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with God he was taken away.</hi> So though her body muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the duſt, vntill the laſt reſurrection, yet her death was ſo eaſy, that it ſeemed rather to be a <hi>Change,</hi> then a <hi>Death;</hi> rather a <hi>Bleſſed Aſſumption,</hi> then a <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent diſſolution:</hi> Now ſhe found to her endleſſe comfort, that with Mary <hi>She had choſen the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, which ſhould not be taken away from her.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Our Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs all for our application
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6179:20"/> learne of a woman of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſex: eſpecially woemen, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate her in her <hi>Piety,</hi> in her <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> of ſpirit, in her <hi>obedience to her Huſband,</hi> her <hi>Modeſty,</hi> her <hi>Grauity, Mildneſſe</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> in her <hi>Charity;</hi> Imitate her in her <hi>Life,</hi> that you may be like her in her <hi>Death;</hi> Imitate her in her <hi>Grace,</hi> that you may be partaker of <hi>her Glory: Make choyce of this part, which ſhall neuer be taken from you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is good, ſo it is perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: Many excellent earthly bleſſings are beſtowed vpon ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God: <hi>Sed pereunt cum pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unte,</hi> they periſh with the vſing, either they will leaue vs, or wee muſt leaue them, but whoſoeuer doth inherite this part, ſhall keepe it without feare of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Maries</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</note> 
               <hi>Non auferetur,</hi> It ſhall not be taken from them. <hi>Mary</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6179:20"/> that all things vnder the Sunne are vanity, and therefore ſhee made <hi>choyce of the better part, which ſhall neuer be taken from her.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Maries</hi> imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So this <hi>Mary</hi> had many out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſings, which fleſh and bloud might haue reioyced in; Shee was well deſcended, but ſhe conſidered that of all other vanities, Honour is but a vayne title: For her perſon, a comely and graue Matron; but ſhee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred what <hi>Salomons</hi> Mother ſaith: That <hi>fauour is deceitfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 31.30.</note> 
               <hi>and beauty vanity, but the woman that feareth the Lord, ſhee ſhall be prayſed.</hi> She liued very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably with a louing and kind Husband; yet ſhee knew that once they muſt part. God bleſſed her with plenty in the world; but ſhee knew that riches are vncertaine: For long life
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6179:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6179:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6179:22"/> that ſhe knew by her owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that <hi>longa vita, eſt lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga agritudo,</hi> long life is a long ſickeneſſe, the things that were vantage vnto her, ſhee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted loſſe for Chriſts ſake; as ſhe ſaid the ſame day ſhe departed, <hi>Shee would not change her eſtate, in that ſhee was remouing out of the body to the Lord, for all the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</note>For our application let vs imitate her happy choice, ſet our affections on things that are aboue, and not on things that are on the earth, weane our ſelues from the loue of theſe worldly vanities, which at laſt wee muſt looſe or leaue, and ſet our ſelues to attaine this <hi>good part, which ſhall neuer bee taken from vs:</hi> To haue Chriſt dwell in our hearts in this world, that wee may dwell with him in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6179:22"/> world to come, where is true <hi>Nobility,</hi> in that wee ſhall bee <hi>Heires</hi> &amp; <hi>Co-heires</hi> with Chriſt: where is true <hi>Honour,</hi> in that we ſhall bee crowned with the crown of righteouſneſſe: where is true <hi>Beauty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.43.</note> in that we ſhine as the <hi>Sun</hi> for euermore: where we ſhall haue long life, <hi>euen life euerlaſting:</hi> where we ſhall haue true <hi>Riches,</hi> an immortall <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> reſerued for vs in the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens:</hi> where for <hi>the Company of our deareſt freinds whom wee loue beſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhall enioy the company of holy Angels, bleſsed Saints,</hi> euen the preſence of God, <hi>Where is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ioy &amp; at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for euermore:</hi> where we ſhall haue more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort &amp; happines in one day, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, poſſibly we could haue in ten thouſand vpon earth, if the world ſhould make vs her Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6179:23"/> and (which is worth all) we ſhall enioy them with a <hi>Non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferentur,</hi> neuer to bee taken from vs. Let vs then caſt downe our ſelues at Chriſts feet, that wee may with <hi>Mary</hi> haue <hi>euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> Let vs with this <hi>Mary</hi> liue like Saints in this world, that with <hi>Mary</hi> and the reſt of the Saints wee may be glorified in the world to come: Which the Lord grant vnto vs all for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, that ſits at the right hand of God in heauen, to whom with the holy Ghoſt, one God, and three perſons be aſcribed all Honour, Glory, Power, praiſe, Dominion, and Thankſ-giuing of vs, and all creatures, now and euermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6179:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
